azstateparks.com 2018-06-13

# Privacy Policy | Arizona State Parks

### State of Arizona Arizona State Parks Privacy Policy Statement

Thank you for visiting the Arizona State Parks and Trails website and reviewing our privacy policy statement. Arizona State Parks and Trails provides information and services specific to Arizona state parks and natural areas within Arizona as well as links to affiliates and organizations that partner with our agency. This statement is included to inform you solely about the information that could be collected online as a result of visiting Arizona State Parks and Trails itself and not as a result of following a link from Arizona State Parks adn Trails to reach a partnering entity’s website or online service. All individual agency websites of the State of Arizona are required to contain a privacy policy statement that describes what information is being obtained online, how that information will be used, and what steps are being taken to ensure the security of customer data. Your rights to privacy are of utmost importance to us at Arizona State Parks and Trails in building trust and confidence when conducting business through the internet.

### Online Customer Service and Alternatives

Arizona State Parks and Trails offers many of the services online that you might otherwise transact in person. Our goal is to provide citizens with a more convenient and efficient means in which to interact with Arizona government. If at any time you choose not to proceed with a transaction offered through the Arizona State Parks and Trails website, your choice will in no way affect your ability to receive benefits or services. If you prefer to receive benefits or services in person, you may do so at our agency location.

### Collection and Use of Information

**Use of Information Provided by the Visitor**

  When a visitor elects to receive information his or her contact information is used for the sole purpose of sending the requested materials. This contact information is not shared, sold, or otherwise disseminated by Arizona State Parks and Trails.

**_Subscribing to the monthly Parks Newsletter  
 _**  
Using a comment form, Arizona State Parks and Trails requires the name and email address of visitors who wish to receive by email our monthly parks newsletter and calendar of events. All other form fields are optional.

  **_Unsubscribing to the Parks Newsletter_**

  You may opt out of the parks newsletter at any time by clicking on "unsubscribe," which is located at the bottom of every issue of the newsletter.

_**Subscribing to the Volunteer eNewsletter**_

  Using an online submission form, Arizona State Parks and Trails requires the name and email address of visitors who wish to receive by email our quarterly Volunteer newsletter. All other form fields are optional. Arizona State Parks and Trails uses a double opt-in subscription method. This means the email address you provide us must be valid and that you have access to it. After signing up, you will receive a confirmation email. You must click the link in that email in order to subscribe to the volunteer eNewsletter.

  _**Unsubscribing to the Volunteer eNewsletter**_

  You may opt out of the volunteer eNewsletter at any time by clicking on "unsubscribe," which is located at the bottom of every issue of the newsletter.

_**Subscribing to the OHV Monthly Newsletter**_

  Using a comment form, Arizona State Parks and Trails requires the name and email address of visitors who wish to receive by email our monthly OHV monthly newsletter. All other form fields are optional.

  _**Unsubscribing to the OHV Monthly Newsletter**_

  You may opt out of the OHV monthly newsletter at any time by clicking on "unsubscribe," which is located at the bottom of every issue of the newsletter.

**Information Collected and Stored Automatically**

The Arizona State Parks and Trails website uses cookies. A “cookie” is a small text file that contains a string of alphanumeric characters. This site uses session cookies. A session cookie is held temporarily in your computer’s memory and disappears after you close your browser or shut off your computer. This session cookie helps the Arizona State Parks and Trails research and marketing department analyze how users interact with the website. No personally identifiable information is stored in this cookie.

  You can set your browser to refuse all cookies or to indicate when a cookie is being set.

  In the future, Arizona State Parks and Trails may use persistent cookies which remain on your hard drive until you erase them or they expire. Persistent cookies could enhance subsequent website visits, and/or speed up or enhance our website's services or functions.

For videos that are embedded, a persistent flash-based cookie is set by third-party providers when you click to play the video. This persistent cookie is used by some third-party providers to help maintain the integrity of video statistics. To change your Flash-based privacy settings [visit this link](http://www.macromedia.com/support/documentation/en/flashplayer/help/settings_manager06.html#117645 "Flash-based privacy settings") where you can also delete any flash-based cookies.

The web server that hosts Arizona State Parks and Trails does gather certain information about the visit automatically in a standard log file. This information never identifies you personally and consists of only the following items:

1\. The Internet domain (for example, "xcompany.com" if you use a private Internet access account, or "yourschool.edu" if you connect from a university's domain) from which you access the website;

2\. The IP address (an IP address is a number that is automatically assigned to your computer whenever you are surfing the Web) from which you access the website; and

3\. The date and time of your access.

We do not automatically record information about you as an individual.

_**Information You Provide**_

Information collected from an application submitted online will be treated in the same manner as the information collected from an application submitted on a hard copy to Arizona State Parks and Trails. The information you disclose to us will generally become a matter of public record pursuant to A. R. S. §§ 39-121, et seq., which means that the agency may be required to divulge certain information in response to a public records request or in response to a warrant, subpoena, or other court order.

Arizona State Parks and Trails may require that you enter personal information (e.g., your name, home address, and credit card number) when requesting certain goods or services described on our website. Those services may also reference common infrastructure utilities that are provided by Arizona @ Your Service. These utilities provide the agency with a means to obtain specific information or to facilitate a specific functional requirement of the online transaction being requested.

As an example, Arizona @ Your Service maintains a central credit card payment interface that Arizona State Parks uses as part of our online gift shop service. This utility will accept only the pertinent credit card authorization data necessary to validate and fulfill the purchase. The cardholder's name, credit card number, and expiration date are obtained by the utility and used only to complete the credit card payment portion of the online transaction. The data is used only for the fulfillment of the payment and is not retained by Arizona @ Your Service.

Not all online applications use the services of Arizona @ Your Service, nor are they required to. Please be assured that your personal information will be held in strictest confidence while Arizona State Parks processes your online transaction and will not be shared, sold, or otherwise disseminated to any outside person or entity, except as required or authorized by law.

Please refer to respective benefits and/or services web pages of our agency for disclosure of when, how, and to whom specific information will be released to third parties, as specified by A.R.S. § 41-4152 (5) and (6). If you have further questions regarding how Arizona State Parks and Trails will use the information you submit online, please contact Arizona State Parks and Trails.

_**Third Party Disclosure**_

Third party organizations contracted with the State of Arizona may provide certain services available on the state’s behalf. Personal information collected through the web portal and/or over-the-counter may be provided to third party service providers to help the state deliver benefits and services. The state will take prudent steps to ensure that third-party organizations are obligated to secure and protect personal information on the State’s behalf.

_**Information Collected from Children**_

By statute, all state agencies must comply with the Children’s Online Privacy Policy Protection Act of 1998 (“COPPA”), requiring parental consent before collecting any personal information from any individual under the age of 13. The text of COPPA is available at <http://www.ftc.gov/ogc/coppa1.htm>.

_**Security**_

The State of Arizona and its consultants, as developer and manager of Arizona State Parks and Trails website, have taken several steps to safeguard the integrity of its computer systems and networks. These steps include, but are not limited to individual authentication, the security of transmitted data, security monitoring, auditing, and encryption of your information. Security methods and measures have been integrated into the design, implementation and day-to-day practices of the entire Arizona State Parks and Trails website.

### External Link Disclaimer

Links to external sites are indicated with the following external link icon:   
These links will open in a new window and leave the Arizona State Parks and Trails website.

Arizona State Parks and Trails contains links to various other websites operated by other government agencies, nonprofit organizations and private businesses. When you follow an external link to another site, you are no longer on the Arizona State Parks website and this Privacy Policy will not apply to other sites. When you follow an external link to another website, you are subject to the privacy policy of that new site. Links to websites outside of state government are offered solely for your convenience; they do not constitute an endorsement and are not a recommendation of any product, service, or organization.

The State of Arizona is not responsible for and has no control over the policies or content of any third-party sites. Any concerns or comments related to the contents of the sites accessed through external links should be directed to the author of that website. Use of any information obtained from such external links is voluntary, and reliance on it should only be undertaken after an independent review of its accuracy, completeness, efficacy, and timeliness.

Neither the State of Arizona, nor any agency, officer, employee, or contractor of the State of Arizona warrants the accuracy, reliability, or timeliness of any information published by external sites, nor endorses any content, viewpoints, products, or services linked from external sites, and shall not be held liable for any losses caused by reliance on the accuracy, reliability or timeliness of such information. Portions of such information may be inaccurate or outdated. Any person or entity that relies on any information obtained from external sites does so at his or her own risk.

### Copyright & Trademark Information

Any and all documents available from this website may be protected under the U.S. and Foreign Copyright Laws. Permission to reproduce may be required.

Unlike the U.S. Federal Government and many of its agencies, the photographs, graphics, maps, and podcasts created by Arizona State Parks are  **not**  in the public domain. All rights are reserved. Unauthorized use is prohibited without the express written consent of Arizona State Parks and Trails. Unless otherwise noted, photography copyright © Arizona State Parks and Trails.

Kartchner Caverns State Park®, Kubla Khan®, and the Arizona State Parks logo (a stylized cactus and water with tree) are federally registered trademarks of Arizona State Parks and Trails. All rights are reserved.

The State of Arizona retains all rights to the information provided by this website, including, but not limited to, the right of distribution.

### Contact Information

To offer comments about Arizona State Parks and Trails, or about the information presented in this Privacy Policy, contact Arizona State Parks and Trails Marketing Department:

By Email: [[email protected]](https://web.archive.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection)

By Telephone: (602) 542-4174

By Mail: Arizona State Parks   
Attn: Marketing   
23751 N 23rd Ave., #190   
Phoenix, Arizona 85085

Email or other information requests sent to a state website may be saved and used to respond to the request, forward the request to the appropriate agency, communicate updates to the state site that may be of interest to citizens, or provide the agency with customer feedback to assist in improving the website.

If you choose to provide us with personal information — by submitting an online form or contacting us by the above methods — we use that information to respond to your message and to help us get you the information you have requested. We only share the information you provide with another agency if your inquiry relates to that agency, or as otherwise required by law. Moreover, we do not create an individual profile with the information you provide or give it to any private organizations. Arizona State Parks and Trails does not collect information for commercial marketing. Any comments collected are themselves subject to the protections of the privacy policy.

### Privacy Policy Statement Is Subject To Change

This Privacy Policy Statement is subject to change _._  Last updated June 2016.
